<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A testimony concerning the life and death of Jane Whitehead that faithful servant and hand-maid of the Lord, who was a mother in Israel, and her memorial is blessed of the Lord for ever : concerning her sufferings, and her faithfulness in her testimony in sufferings : with an exhortation to turn to the true light, in a few words to all backsliders from the truth / by a lover of truth and righteousness, who hath a testimony against oppression, cruelty, and persecution, wheresoever I see it appear against the innocent, T.T.</title>
            <author>Townsend, Theophila.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63021</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1989</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23565</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12072980</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12072980</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53533</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63021)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53533)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 583:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A testimony concerning the life and death of Jane Whitehead that faithful servant and hand-maid of the Lord, who was a mother in Israel, and her memorial is blessed of the Lord for ever : concerning her sufferings, and her faithfulness in her testimony in sufferings : with an exhortation to turn to the true light, in a few words to all backsliders from the truth / by a lover of truth and righteousness, who hath a testimony against oppression, cruelty, and persecution, wheresoever I see it appear against the innocent, T.T.</title>
                  <author>Townsend, Theophila.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Theophila Townsend.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Whitehead, Jane, d. 1674.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53533:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53533:1"/>
            <p>A TESTIMONY Concerning the LIFE and DEATH OF Jane Whitehead, THAT Faithful Servant and Hand-maid of the Lord, who was a Mother in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and her Memorial is bleſſed of the Lord for ever. Concerning her Sufferings, and her Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs in her Teſtimony in Sufferings. With an Exhortation to turn to the True Light, in a few words to all Backſliders from the Truth, by a Lover of Truth and Righteouſneſs, who hath a Teſtimony againſt Oppreſſion, Cruelty, and Perſecution, whereſoever I ſee it appear againſt the Innocent. <hi>T. T.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Thus ſaith the Lord by his Servant the Prophet, Woe to them that decree <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous decrees, and write grievouſneſs, which they preſcribe to turn aſide the needy from Judgment, and to take away the right from the poor of my people, that Widdows may be their Prey, and that they may rob the Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs: But what will you do in the day of Viſitation, and in the Deſolation that ſhall come from far? To whom will you fly for help, or where will you leave your glory?</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſaiah 10.1, 2, 3.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Bleſsed are the dead that die in the Lord, for they reſt from their labours, and their Works do follow them,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rev. 13.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year 1676.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:53533:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:53533:2"/>
            <head>A Testimony concerning <hi>Jane Whitehead,</hi> Wife of <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Whitehead</hi> of <hi>South Cadbury</hi> in the County of <hi>Summerſet,</hi> late Deceaſed; whoſe former name was <hi>Jane Waugh,</hi> that faithful Servant and Handmaid of the Lord, whoſe Memorial is bleſſed for ever, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of her uprightneſs and ſtedfaſtneſs of heart and mind unto the Lord from the firſt to the laſt, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan in the true Faith, and kept in it unto the end of her dayes, by which ſhe obtained Victory, and was made more than a Conqueror (through Christ that loved her) over all her enemies, both within, and without, and hath now finiſhed her courſe in this world, and hath obtained an entrance into that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlasting glorious Reſt, heavenly Felicity, and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Conſolation that the Lord hath prepared for them that truly love him and keep their Confidence in him, and hold faſt their Integrity for him unto the end of their dayes, as this true and faithful follower of the Lamb hath done, and now hath received of the Lord an immortal Crown of Life and endleſs Glory, as the Reward of her Faithfulneſs from the hand of a tender Father, who never fails any that truly truſt in him, but is an exceeding great Reward unto all the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right in Heart.</head>
            <p>THis Teſtimony is ſealed in my heart by the Spirit of the Lord concerning the everlaſting Happineſs, and endleſs Well-being of this my dear Friend and Siſter in the Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53533:3"/>Relation, unto whom my Soul was, and is truly united in the Unity of the Spirit in the bleſſed Covenant of life in which in the remembrance of her faithfulneſs my ſoul is truly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed: Therefore we have good cauſe to ſay that the Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial of the Righteous is bleſſed, as one ſaid in the dayes of old, that They ſhall be had in everlaſting remembrance among thoſe that fear the Lord: So my dear Siſter, the living remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of thee hath often tender'd my heart before the Lord in the conſideration of his goodneſs, and the largeneſs of his Mercy in thy Preſervation, who hath kept thee by his migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty power in faithfulneſs to himſelf in thy holy Teſtimony through all thy Tryals and Exerciſes that thou haſt met with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all from a cruel and hard hearted Generation; cruel Mockings, Scoffings, and Scorning, Beating and Reviling, ond cruel Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonments in naſty places in the cold of Winter, and heat of Summer.</p>
            <p>Thus, thou Renowned of the Lord, did the cruel hearted deal with thee for thy bleſſed Teſtimony ſake, that thou brought'ſt among them in the Love of God, and in love to their own poor ſouls; but they rejecting their own mercies, thus requited thee, and evily intreated thee for thy love to them; but thy reward is with the Lord for ever, who hath bleſſed thy Labour and Travel, and made it very effectual and proſperous, and very acceptable unto the honeſt hearted, that were ſeeking after the Lord, who received thy bleſſed Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony with gladneſs of heart; and the Lord bleſſed thy Labours in his Work and Service, who endued thee with power from on high, to ſpeak a word in ſeaſon to ſeveral States and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, and to reach the Witneſs of God in their Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to the awakening many to righteouſneſs, and the bleſſed power of the mighty God was with thee, and his living Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence did ſweetly accompany thee in that bleſſed work which he called thee to, in which thou waſt faithful and diligent, according to the meaſure of Grace committed to thee.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:53533:3"/>
            <p>Oh thou deareſt unto me of many, and never to be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by me becauſe of thy ſpotleſs life, who hath kept thy Garments clean from all manner of defilements and ſpots of the wicked World! Oh thou bleſſed of the Lord, how often hath my heart been broken into tears of true ſorrow becauſe of the want of thee, as to thy bodily preſence, becauſe of thy tender care over the Family of God; for true Uprightneſs is very pretious to me amongſt thoſe that have a Teſtimony for the Lord, which is the garment of Praiſe; and becauſe of thy Uprightneſs was my heart joyned unto thee, my dear Friend, and well beloved in the Lord, who hath now taken thee away out of the reach of all thy enemies, thou true Jew, whoſe praiſe is not of men but of God; who didſt not appear outwardly beyond what the Lord had made thee by the virtue of his Divine power, and ſanctifying Spirit, that hath wrought mightily in thee, to the effecting the work of Mortification and Humiliation, and true Self-denyal in thee, and hath filled thy heart with his Love, and with the virtue of his bleſſed Life, by which thou waſt prepared and made a veſſel of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in the hand of the Lord, the ſweet ſavour of whoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Life abides with us, though thou art gone from us as to the outward enjoyment of thee; but thy life, thy innocent life is with us, and will remain with us for ever, when all the enemies that hate it, and have hunted after it to deſtroy it, ſhall not be able to ſtand before it; for it will out-live all the wrath of man, and all the fury of the wicked, and is out of the reach of every envious mind, which length of time ſhall never wear out, becauſe it is everlaſting in which thy dwelling place is, and will be for ever, thou dear Servant and Child of the moſt high God, who hath bleſſed thee, and will not have thy Uprightneſs be forgotten, nor thy Faithfulneſs buryed in the Grave of Oblivion; for the Lord God of Life by the word of his power hath often preſſed me in Spirit very weightily,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53533:4"/>and his living Word hath run through my heart in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of thee, for Righteouſneſs muſt not be forgotten, nor her Uprightneſs and Faithfulneſs be buryed in the Grave of Oblivion; for the Righteouſneſs of the Righteous ſhall be upon them, and they ſhall ſhine as the Stars for ever and ever, and their Memorial is and ſhall be bleſſed now hence forth and for ever.</p>
            <p>Now that all People might know, unto whom this may come, that it is not in any vain boaſting or exaltation of any created excellency, or worthineſs of any mortal Creature that I thus write, but it is purely in honour to that excellency and comelineſs, beauty and worthyneſs of that bleſſed Life of Righteouſneſs in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord and Saviour, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he hath beautified his people; by the virtue of whoſe bleſſed power, and weighty Life, I am conſtrained to give this Teſtimony for my dear deceaſed Friend, of whom I have had good knowledge for fourteen years or more, who came into this County in the Service of the Lord, an innocent Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man with her, one <hi>Frances Raunce,</hi> that then was her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, who is entered into reſt with her, and was a fellow Labourer with her in the ſame Work and Service, and the power and preſence of the Lord was with them, who bleſſed their labour to the confirming of many in the truth, and to the ſtrengthning of the Weak, and the comforting of the upright in heart, who were refreſhed by them through the bleſſed power and holy preſence of the Lord which did accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany them, which was about fourteen years ago; they tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled together, and now have their reward together with joy in the Lord: <hi>J. R.</hi> was Wife to <hi>John R.</hi> of <hi>High-wickham,</hi> a Virtuous Woman that feared God in her day; ſhe dyed ſome years before <hi>J. W.</hi> and I can truly ſay, that in all this time I never knew any evil by her neither in word nor deed, nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard of any one that could juſtly charge her with any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53533:4"/>although ſhe had many enemies, yet it was for Righteouſneſs ſake, and not for evil doing, but becauſe ſhe bore a Teſtimony againſt the World, that the deeds thereof are evil, therefore the world hated her, and riſe up againſt her to perſecute her, which ſhe hath received at their hands with Patience and Meekneſs, truly deſiring the Welfare of her Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, that they might come to Repentance and amendment of Life, that they might find Mercy with the Lord, ſo that their Souls might be ſaved from the wrath that is to come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all that rebel againſt the Light, and are enemies to the Croſs of Chriſt, and are haters of thoſe which are good, and perſecutors of them that truly fear God, and live in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to his pure Law that is written in their hearts, and are led by the Spirit which he hath put into their inward parts, ſuch who love his bleſſed appearance in the bright ſhining of his heavenly divine Light to the opening of their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, and making known the Myſteries of his Kingdom unto them; I ſay, thoſe that hate ſuch, and riſe up againſt them to perſecute them, the Lord will plead with them, and will pour out of his Judgments, and Wrath, and Vengeance upon them, in his own ſeaſon, as he hath done upon ſome of the Perſecuters of this innocent Lamb before-mentioned, whom the Lord hath taken away out of their reach, and hath received up into Glory, of whom that ungodly Generation was not worthy, becauſe of their hard heartedneſs towards her, and cruel dealings with her, as in the following Relation may be ſpecifyed more fully.</p>
            <p>In the year 1655. the ſaid <hi>Jane Waugh,</hi> an innocent Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that truly feared God, who in obedience to him came out of her own Countrey from the County of <hi>Weſtmoreland,</hi> her Relations living at <hi>Hutton</hi> in the ſame County, whom ſhe left in obedience to the Lord, to travel in his Service, and to do his holy Will whereſoever he was pleaſed to order her by the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53533:5"/>Word of his Power to bear Witneſs againſt the falſe wayes and Worſhips of the World, amongſt whom for her Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhe received many reproachful Revilings, and Abuſes, and Smitings with the Fiſts of Wickedneſs, as many can witneſs who are yet alive in and about <hi>Banbury</hi> in <hi>Oxfordſhire;</hi> and in the year before-mentioned, ſhe came to <hi>Banbury</hi> in <hi>Oxfordſhire</hi> to viſit her impriſoned Friend <hi>Anne Audtand,</hi> an innocent Woman that feared the Lord, who was a Priſoner for the Teſtimony of Jeſus, and the Word of God; and when ſhe came to that Town, ſhe beholding their Cruelty, Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Hardheartedneſs, ſhe bearing witneſs for the Truth, and againſt their Wickedneſs, ſhe was taken and brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Magiſtrates, one <hi>John Aſtin</hi> Mayor, and <hi>William Allen</hi> Juſtice of the Peace, ſo called; who when they had examin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her, ſent her to Priſon, though no evil could be charged againſt her, where ſhe ſuffered five weeks Impriſonment, and then releaſed her for that time.</p>
            <p>But not long after ſhe came to <hi>Banbury</hi> again, and as ſhe was with a Friend to write her a Letter, the Magiſtrates hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of her, being moved with envy to Perſecution, ſent for her to be brought before them, who being bent to do Wickly by her, tendered the Oath of Abjuration to her to enſnare her, who in obedience to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ſaith <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> refuſed it, for which thoſe cruel hearted men ſent her to Priſon again, where ſhe ſuffered twelve months Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, the cold Winter ſeaſon in a low damp naſty place, that ſometimes would be over the ſhooes in water, as I have heard her often ſay: Such was their Cruelty, and Hardheart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs to this tender Woman that truly feared God, and bore a living Teſtimony for his holy Name, through all theſe Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties and Sufferings which ſhe received at their hands with Patience; but thoſe abuſes brought her tender body into Weakneſs, which ſhe hath been attended with for ſeveral
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53533:5"/>years before her departure, through the Cruelty of her Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors, who were not yet ſatisfied in their Cruelty towards her, though no evil could be charged againſt her from the firſt to the laſt. When ſhe came to <hi>Banbury</hi> again in the fourth month, 1662. where ſhe was at a Meeting with the people of God, called Quakers, to wait upon the Lord in his Fear; for which ſhe was taken and brought before the Magiſtrates, one <hi>Thomas Robbins</hi> Mayor, and <hi>William Wheatly</hi> Juſtice, and by them unjuſtly committed to that naſty Priſon again, where ſhe ſuffered three months more, by the wicked Oppreſſors of <hi>Banbury,</hi> which ſhe bore all patiently, and never was ſlack in her Teſtimony, but was bold for the Lord, and his holy Truth, notwitſtanding all the rage of the Wicked; for ſhe would not defile her Conſcience for fear of the Wrath of man, but ſhe feared the living God, and committed her innocent cauſe unto the Lord, who pleaded for her in his own ſeaſon with her Enemies and Oppreſſors, in taking Vegeance upon them, by ſmiting ſome of them in an eminent manner; one of them was ſuddenly ſmitten when he was going from home, ſo that he was not able to help himſelf, which he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver recovered till he dyed; and others of them did the Lords hand follow till the Family of them was laid waſte; ſo as it was ſaid in the dayes of old, the Lord ſhall appear to render Vengeance on them that trouble you, but to you that are troubled, peace and reſt with the Lord; ſo notwithſtanding all her trouble, her Soul now reſteth in peace with the Lord for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>All this was when ſhe was unmarried that ſhe ſuffered at <hi>Banbury,</hi> and after this was over, and ſhe at liberty again, ſhe travelled through theſe parts, and went down Weſtward, where the Lord gave her to an honeſt man, and ſhe became his Wife, and they lived very comfortably together, and had five goodly Children after they were marryed together, which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53533:6"/>ſhe hath left behind her with her true Husband, which hath given a good Teſtimony for her of her faithfulneſs, and alſo of her Sufferings whilſt ſhe was his Wife, for ſhe was not then free from Sufferings, becauſe ſhe continued in Faithfulneſs to the ſame bleſſed Teſtimony, for which the Enemies of the Lord roſe up againſt her in the beginning, for ſhe bore Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the Light of Chriſt Jeſus, that he is the true Light that lighteth every man that cometh into the World, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>John</hi>'s Teſtimony, that was a man ſent from God, <hi>John</hi> 1.9. to bear Witneſs to the ſame bleſſed Light, who alſo ſaid of him, in him was Life, and the Life was the Light of men, ſo it is the Light of Jeſus that is the Light of men; and this is the Teſtimony that <hi>John</hi> bare of the true Light, which the World that lies in Wickedneſs Hates and Perſecutes, Reviſes and Villifies, the blind Formal Profeſſors, as well as open Prophane, as the Jews and Phariſees. did by our Lord and Maſter when he was viſible upon the earth, who wickedly ſaid he had a Devil, and that he caſt out Devils by Beelzebub the Prince of Devils, ſo the Servant is not greater than his Lord, as he ſaid at that day; and the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture bears Teſtimony of the ſame.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:53533:6"/>
            <head>Here followeth her H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBAND'S Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony concerning her.</head>
            <p>AS concerning <hi>Jane Whitehead,</hi> my dear Deceaſed VVife, whoſe Maiden Name was <hi>Jane Wough,</hi> this is my Teſtimony concerning her, That ſhe was one that feared God, and wrought Righteouſneſs and did in all things both in her Life and Converſation, endeavour to keep a Conſcience void of Offence tovvards God, and all men; and did endeavour, as much as in her lay, according to the Gift of Grace given unto her, to keep the Unity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace, vvith all the Faithful; yet ſtill nevertheleſs vvhen ſhe did apprehend any thing to be amiſs among thoſe that did Profeſs the Truth, ſhe vvould in much uprightneſs of heart, vvithout Partiality, deal plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vvith them, as is vvell knovvn by Friends in thoſe parts; and vvhen ſhe had a ſenſe upon her of that Spirits entrance upon any, under any pretence or likeneſs vvhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, that vvould ſovv Diſcord, and break the Concord and Unity among Friends and Brethren: With vvhat grief of heart and Soul have I heard her complain of it, and ſeen her with Diligence endeavour to ſtop it! For truly it vvas the great joy of her Heart, and Comfort of her Soul to be in the Company of Upright-hearted Friends, and to keep in the Fellowſhip of the Goſpel of Chriſt Jeſus, vvith the Brotherhood: And ſhe vvas alvvayes of an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53533:7"/>heart to Diſtribute to the Neceſſity of the Saints; and vvas ready, according to Truth's Requirings, to ſerve the Truth and Friends in any thing ſhe could, and never thought ſhe could do too much for thoſe that truly fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſerved the Lord in their Generation; And ſhe being called forth neer about tvventy years ago, and a neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty laid upon her from the Lord to bear VVitneſs unto the true Light that lighteth every man that cometh into the VVorld, vvhich had ſhined in her Heart and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, unto vvhich Call of the Lord ſhe became obedient, and gave her Back to the Smiter, and her Cheek to them that have not ſpared their Cruelty tovvards her; Yea ſhe took up the Croſs, and deſpiſed the Shame, for the Joy that vvas ſet before her; For I have heard her ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſay, that if it might have ſtood vvith the VVill of Lord, ſhe could have rather choſed to dye, than to have undergone thoſe things that lay upon her; for ſhe vvas many times called forth after her firſt Convincement, to bear VVitneſs in the Steeple-houſes to the Truth, againſt their Falſe VVorſhip, vvhere ſhe met vvith much hard Uſage from the Savage People, and a great deal of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach from her Relations and Acquaintance, beyond vvhat may eaſily be expreſſed, though aftervvards, they ſeeing her Integrity, became very Loving and Reſpective to her.</p>
            <p>And ſhe vvas ſometimes caſt into Priſons, vvhere ſhe vvas faithful in her Teſtimony, till the Lord made vvay for her Deliverance; And many times, as ſhe Travelled in obedience to the Lord on Truths account, ſhe ſuffered much Hardſhip in the outvvard, a great deal of hard Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, Hunger and Cold; yet ſhe ſaid in much tenderneſs of heart, and in the ſenſe of the Lords Love, that he could make a Cup of cold VVater as good to her as VVine; and ſhe ſaid at that time, it vvas as pretious unto her, although it
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53533:7"/>was a time unto her in which ſhe Travelled as in a Land un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſown; yet bleſſed be the Lord, the effects of her Labour, Travels, and Sufferings have in many places of this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on been ſeen, ſhe having been an Inſtrument in the hand of the Lord, for the Convincing and turning of many to Righteouſneſs, from Darkneſs to Light, and from Satans Power to God; to which end the Lord endued her with his Heavenly Gift, and made her Miniſtry effectual, as many can bear Witneſs for her, though of her ſelf ſhe was weak and could do nothing, yet had Faith in Chriſt, who enabling her, could do all things that he called her unto: And ſince ſhe came into theſe parts, the Lord hath made her Miniſtry very effectual, through his Heavenly Gift, to the Eſtabliſhing, and Confirming of many in Gods ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Truth, and his Heavenly Preſence did much ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company her, and oft fill her Veſſel, and his Power was in her Miniſtry, that the Weak were Comforted, and thoſe that were ready to Faint, were abundantly refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as many in thoſe parts can truly bear her Witneſs; and through all her Service in the Labour of the Goſpel this was her Comfort, as I heard her ſeveral times ſay, That ſhe never ſought her ſelf, as ſhe could appeal to the Lord, and to the Conſciences of all people where ſhe had Travelled, but for the good of Souls, and the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gods bleſſed Name, and his everlaſting Truth: Yea, I may truly Teſtifie on her behalf, that ſhe coveted no mans Silver and Gold, nor Apparel; for what ſhe had of her own ſhe ſpent on Truth's account before ſhe was my Wife, and ſince, when the Lord hath laid a neceſſity up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her to Travel in his work and Service, ſhe hath had freely of me, and the Lord hath bleſſed us ſo that we never wanted any thing. And this I give as a Teſtimony againſt the vain imaginations that have riſen in the minds of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53533:8"/>ſome Carnal Profeſſors in thoſe parts: And truly the Lord made her a bleſſing unto me in many Reſpects, whoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret hand did bring us together; and now hath taken her from me again, who was ſo neer and dear unto me; and ſhe is out of the reach of all her Enemies and Perſecuters, and thoſe that did hate her for the Goſpels ſake, and is at Reſt with the Lord, with whom is her Reward for ever and ever Yea, <hi>Bleſſed are the Dead that dye in the Lord, they reſt from their Labours, and their works ſhall follow them.</hi> And that which remains as a deſire in my heart is, That I may ſerve the ſame God to the end of my dayes, who never failed her, under any Exerciſe or Tryal that ſhe was accompanyed with; for when the Officers ſometimes were taking our Goods for to levy a Fine for a Meeting, they asked her whether we did ſtill intend to keep Meetings? and ſhe anſwered as it was in her heart, Yes, we reſolve to follow the Lord fully.</p>
            <p>Moreover, under the great Exerciſe or weakneſs of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy that ſhe was in before her departure, ſhe often acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged that the Lord was wonderful good unto her, for though ſometimes ſhe might be under ſome Exerciſe of mind by reaſon of her great Weakneſs, yet ſhe was kept quiet and patient, and did often ſay, That the Lord had broke in upon her, and with his Heavenly Preſence did fill her to the Comfort of her Soul, and the Joy of Heart as ſhe did many times acknowledge, and ſaid, <hi>O that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> may never take his preſence from me!</hi> It was ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> pretious and deſirable unto her; and bleſſed be the Lord, he was good unto her to the very laſt, ſhe was kept ſenſible, and did acknowledge that ſhe had the Teſtimony of his Love, and that it would be well with her, and that ſhe had no deſire to live any longer in this World: and a little before her depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſhe had no deſire to have her Children with her, though
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53533:8"/>they were very neer &amp; dear unto her; but having given them a Charge to be obedient to their Father, and that they ſhould mind Truth, and then the Bleſſing of the Lord would be with them, ſo ſhe deſired to be retired; and the morning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her Departure, ſhe had a ſenſe that the time of her De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture was at hand, ſo ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a Friend that ſhe was going to her long home; and that morning ſhe deſired me to go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout my occaſions, though all along before ſhe ſtill deſired my Company; and I being ſometime wanting, was called in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, ſhe being now upon Departing, our dear Friend <hi>J. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derdon</hi> being with me, we went in unto her, and he held her by the hand, and I held her up about the neck, and ſhe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted her Senſiblenſs, and her Faithful Conſtant Love to me unto the very laſt, and ſo departed in the Love and Peace of God, as ſeveral had a Teſtimony of it that were there preſent.</p>
            <p>The <hi>28th</hi> day of the <hi>7th</hi> month 74. was the day of her Departure, and ſhe was Buryed the <hi>6th</hi> day of the <hi>8th</hi> month. following, being accompanyed with very many Friends, and many Neighbours.— So <hi>They that are wiſe ſhall ſhine as the brightneſs of the Firmament, and they that turn many to Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs as the Stars for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>South-Gadbury, <date>the <hi>8th</hi> day of the <hi>8th</hi> month, 75.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Thomas Whitehead.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:53533:9"/>
            <head>Here followeth a Relation of more of her Sufferings, the <hi>28th</hi> day of the <hi>9th</hi> Month, <hi>1671.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>JAne Whitehead</hi> was brought to <hi>Ilcheſter</hi> Priſon with a young Child Sucking at her Breaſt, through the Envy and Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs of the Prieſt of <hi>North-Cadbury,</hi> one <hi>John Atwood,</hi> who malitiouſly Swore againſt her, ſhe being accuſed that ſhe came into his Congregation with Force and Arms, and did Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt him and Diſturb his whole Congregation; which was a very Lye, for ſhe neither uſed Force, nor Arms, but ſpake ſoberly in the Fear of God, bearing her Teſtimony for the Truth, againſt the Covetous Practiſes of the Falſe Hirelings, and ſpake the words of Truth and Soberneſs; and we are well ſatisfied that no True Miniſter, nor good People would be offended nor diſturbed at this; yet notwithſtanding, <hi>R.H.</hi> a Juſtice, Committed her to Priſon, from her Husband, and four ſmall Children, and one tender Child ſhe carryed in her Arms, and brought them again from <hi>Ilcheſter</hi> Priſon to the Seſſions at <hi>Wells</hi> in the Winter Seaſon, and through the falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious actions of the Prieſt, ſent her back to Priſon again, where ſhe remained until the <hi>2d</hi> month 72. all the Cold Winter; (yet the Goaler was civil towards her) but the Lord will plead her innocent Cauſe in his own Seaſon, with thoſe her Enemis, as he hath done with other that roſe up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her; for the Lord was with her in the time of her Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:53533:9"/>who did uphold her by the word of his power, and gave her ſtrength and courage to encounter with Truths ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; and bleſſed be his Name for ever, he hath now brought her through the War to Peace and everlaſting Reſt, to ſit down with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> in the Kingdom of God for ever, and hath Crowned her with Victory with a Crown of immortality and eternal Life, Glory over all to the Lord God and the Lamb that ſits upon the Throne.</p>
            <p>Therefore, dear Friends, you that are but young and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, who are convinced of the everlaſting Truth of the living God, and have believed in the Light of his bleſſed Son, Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, this is my Councel in the Love and Councel of the Lord unto you all, That you abide in the Light, and yield all holy Subjection by living in obedience unto it, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Divine operation, and holy requirings of the Spirit of Truth in your inward parts; that you hearken to the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of it, and be willing to be led and guided by it, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive inſtruction from it at all times, and upon all occaſions, that the way of the Lord may become your delight for ever, and the path of the Juſt the place of your footſteps, that ſo through righteouſneſs you may obtain the bleſſing of peace from the hand of the Lord, as your portion for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>Therefore travel on in the ſtrength of the Lord, ye tender Children of the day of Gods everlaſting Love: I ſay, travel on with Courage, with chearful hearts and ready minds in the footſteps of the flock of the holy Companions, as this our dear faithful deceaſed Friend hath done, that ſo you may with the Lords Worthies, Open ye everlaſting doors that the holy Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may come in, that ſo you may come truly to be of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Aſſembly of the Church of the firſt Borne, whoſe names are written in Heaven, and to the innumerable Company of Angels, to the Spirits of Juſt men made perfect, and to God the Judge of all, to receive an Inheritance among them that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53533:10"/>are ſanctified, and have fellowſhip with the Saints in Light, and ſo come to witneſs life and immortality brought to light through the Goſpel of our Lord Chriſt Jeſus, the mighty power of God, to whom be Glory for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is to be obtained by following the holy divine Light, that ſhines in the heart in the dayly Croſs; and true ſelf-denyal of our own wills, in true and holy ſubjection unto the will of God, who hath truly loved us, and gave his Son Chriſt Jeſus for us, who bare the Croſs, and deſpiſed the ſhame, who came not to do his own will, but the will of the Father that ſent him, who was made of no Reputation, though he was Lord of all; he took upon him the form of a Servant, and became obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to the death of the Croſs, and was Scourged for our tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, and bruiſed for our ſins, that we might receive Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption by him, and Salvation through Faith in his blood, and his living and ruling in us, who hath cauſed his heavenly Light to ſhine in our hearts, that by the living virtue of it our underſtandings are opened, whereby we come to ſee him that is inviſible, and to know him that is true, and we are in him that is true, who having finiſhed the work that his Father ſent him to do, is aſcended up on high, and hath led Captivity Captive, and given gifts unto men for the work of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, and for the perfecting of the Saints, and the edifying of the body of Chriſt till all come to a perfect man to the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt, who is ſate down at the right hand of the Majeſty on high, glorified with the Father for ever and ever; yet nevertheleſs he that inhabits eternity al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo dwelleth with the man of a broken heart, and contrite ſpirit, and trembles at his word; of this we have a living experience through the goodneſs and mercy of the Lord unto us, who hath begotten us again by the immortal word of Life, unto a lively hope in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, who is worthy over all to have the praiſes, the glory &amp; honour everlaſting renown with living obedience from all that are made pertakers of the riches of his grace, now henceforth and for ever.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:53533:10"/>
            <head>Here followeth the Teſtimony of <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Jane Ander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> concerning <hi>Jane Whitehead.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THis Teſtimony we have to give for <hi>Jane Whitehead,</hi> that ſhe was a good and honourable Woman in her day and time, the Lord having poured forth his Spirit upon her, as up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on many other of his Servants and Hand-maids in this the day of his power, and ſhe was truly called to the work and ſervice of the Lord, in which ſhe was valiant for the Truth, and feared the Lord in faithfulneſs in her generation, and held the Faith, and kept her Integrity to the laſt &amp; was a good Savour in her life and death, &amp; ſhe is bleſſed, and her good works do follow her, and we never found her too forward to ſpeak in Meetings, or to ſeek the Preheminence, but to clear her Conſcience be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, which was well: We were preſent at her death, and ſhe died like a Lamb, for death was ſwallowed up of life, and ſhe is happy, and gone to her grave in peace with God, and at her Burial her life did preach, and her memorial is bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; and ſhe ſaid a little before ſhe dyed, that the Lord laid no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to her charge, and that the Lord did bear her Witneſs that ſhe never ſought her Self in all her Labour and Travels, in which ſhe met with many exerciſes, even to bonds and Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment for the Teſtimony of Jeſus, and the word of God, in all which he kept and preſerved her faithful to himſelf, even to the end; and ſhe ſpared not iniquity, but took up the Croſs and diſpiſed the ſhame, and is entred into reſt; and ſhe was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous that all ſhould be in truth and reality, what in word they outwardly profeſſed themſelves to be and made a ſhew of; and ſhe could not endure Hypocriſie, but rejoyced in godly Society, and her dear Love was to all Friends, whoſe welfare and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53533:11"/>in the Truth ſhe much deſired, and Peace and Unity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all the Flock of God, that they might keep together under the one Shepheard in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, in the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his eternal Spirit for ever.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Ilcheſter</hi> Priſon, <date>the <hi>14th</hi> day of the <hi>8th</hi> month, 1675.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>John Anderdon, Jane Anderdon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <head>
               <hi>The Testimony of</hi> Jaſper Butt <hi>for</hi> Jane Whitehead.</head>
            <p>I Have known her for neer twenty years paſt, about the time when Truth firſt brake forth in the Southern parts of this Nation; ſhe was one on whom God fulfilled his Promiſe, even a Hand-maid on whom he poured out his Spirit, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companyed with his living Preſence, he having committed a Diſpenſation of the everlaſting Goſpel to her, in which ſhe was faithful according to the meaſure received: And though ſhe was the weaker Veſſel his Power was manifeſted in her, to the reaching of his own Witneſs, and turning many from Darkneſs to the Light, and many Children may riſe up and call her bleſſed, for ſhe was a Mother in <hi>Iſrael:</hi> She came forth neer the beginning of the Lambs War in theſe latter dayes, and was a faithful follower of him, through many Tribulations and Sufferings: The Unity, Peace, and Welfare of the Lords People was precious to her, and ſhe Travelled in many Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of this Nation in the Lords Service, in which his Power and Bleſſing was with her, and minded that more than any Self-intereſt: towards her latter end ſhe had a pretty long
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53533:11"/>time of Weakneſs, her body being in a Conſumption; I was with her a few dayes before her Departure, and was well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed in the ſence of Gods living Preſence manifeſted in her, which truly refreſh'd and comforted her in her outward weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and gave her true content in the will of the Lord, in which ſhe was gathered to her Fathers, and laid down her head in everlaſting Peace, her memory is bleſſed, and her name yields a good ſavour; and in that life into which ſhe gathered whilſt converſant amongſt us, we ſtill enjoy a fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with her, and though dead ſhe yet lives with us, having <hi>Fought the good Fight, and kept the Faith, and finiſhed her Courſe, ſhe hath obtained the Crown laid up in ſtore for them that have the appearance of the Lord Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>The <hi>29th</hi> day of the <hi>11th</hi> month, 1575.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Jaſper Butt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="tract">
            <p>SO my dear Friends, all people to whom this our Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny may come, this is my Exhortation unto you all, that you all tread the ſame path, and walk in the ſame way of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, of righteouſneſs and faithfulneſs that this dear Lamb hath trodden, and mind the ſame thing, and obey the ſame Spirit, that you may have the ſame bleſſed reward, and be made partakers of the ſame everlaſting happineſs and bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, by receiving an entrance, and having an habitation in that Inheritance that ſhall never fade away, that when this earthly Tabernacle ſhall be diſſolved, you may receive a houſe not made with hands eternally in the Heavens, which is the end of all our Labour, and Travels, and Sufferings, that the Lord may be glorified, and peoples Souls may be ſaved from the dreadful day, and terrible Wrath and Vengeance of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53533:12"/>Lord God and the Lamb, which is due to the wicked, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their Wickedneſs, ſin and ungodlineſs, and will be their portion for ever, if they do not repent and turn to the Lord by amendment of life; Yea, Tribulation and Anguiſh upon eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſoul that does evil, upon the Jew firſt, and alſo upon the Gentile; for if Judgment begin firſt at the houſe of God, where ſhall the ſinners and ungodly appear? So you, dear Travellers, that are turned <hi>Sion-ward,</hi> run the race with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience that is ſet before you, even the race of Salvation; and ſo run that ye may obtain the prize, even the Salvation of your Souls; for the race is not to the ſwift, nor the battle to the ſtrong; for though Kings of Armies fly apace, yet the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that ſits at home divides the ſpoil, whoſe feet abide in her own houſe, and goe not into the Chambers of Death.</p>
            <p>Oh my dear Country-men and Women, my neer and dear Relations, Kindred and Acquaintance, for my heart is enlarged for your lakes in the tender Love of God, that hath opened my heart by the bowels of his own Compaſſion, to invite you all, and intreat you all to turn unto the Lord, and ſeek him while he may be found, and call upon him while he is neer, for he is not far from every one of you; therefore turn unto him with your whole hearts, that you may receive at the hands of the Lord, who is a merciful God, even the tenders of Life and Salvation, which he is now holding forth freely in his Son Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, who delighteth not in the death of a ſinner, but had rather that all ſhould turn from the evil of their wayes and live: Therefore I ſay again, Receive the Tenders of his Univerſal Love held forth in the Light of his beloved Son, for in him are all the Promiſes of God, <hi>Yea, and Amen,</hi> for ever; for in him is Salvation and plentious Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for all that put far from them the evil of their doings, who ceaſe to do evil, and learn to do well; then, though their ſins were as ſcarlet, he will make them as ſnow; and though they
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:53533:12"/>were as Crimſon, they ſhall be as Wool; therefore do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, but turn to the Light of his pure Spirit in your own ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoms, that Reproves for ſin in ſecret, and bears witneſs againſt ungodlineſs; for the Scriptures do declare, that God hath not left himſelf without a Witneſs, and this is his faithful Witneſs, even Chriſt Jeſus; therefore turn unto him I beſeech you all unto whom this may come, and ſlight not the day of your Viſitation, leaſt you never have another; for who knows how ſoon the Lord may call you out of this world? then it will be too late to cry to the Lord for mercy, when the Gate of mercy is ſhut, and you left to receive a Reward from the hand of the Lord for your evil deeds done in the body; for there is no Repentance in the Grave, but as the tree falls ſo it lies, and as Death leaves ſo Judgment finds, therefore while you have time Prize it, and come down from the high Mountains of your own caſting up in your vain imaginations, and come, O come into the low Vally of <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi> where the true Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lord is received, for <hi>Zion</hi> is Redeemed through Judgment, and her Converts with Righteouſneſs; for when Judgment is ſet up in the earth, then the Inhabitants thereof learn Righteouſneſs; and the Prophet ſaith, The fruits of Righteouſneſs that ſhall be peace, the effects of it quietneſs and aſſurance for ever; but no peace to the Wicked, ſaith my God; no peace to the Perſecuters of the Lords people, no peace to the Deſpiſers of the true Light of Chriſt within, no peace to the blind Seers, nor ſleepy Watchmen, nor falſe hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Prieſts, that oppreſs the poor, and live by the ſweat of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens brows; no peace to the idle Shepherds that feed with the fat, and cloath with the wool, and make a prey upon the Flock, who pull the ſheaf from the hungry, and the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs from the breaſt, ſuch are they that rebel againſt the Light, who cry peace, peace unto people while they put into their mouths, but when any for good Conſcience ſake refuſe to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:53533:13"/>put into their mouths, then they prepare War againſt them, and fly to the Law to recover treble, or other damage againſt them; no peace to the Backſliders and proud boaſters, who have Apoſtatized from the Truth; and no peace to the falſe hearted, nor double minded, and rebellious, that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet came to the Truth:<note place="margin">No Peace to any of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, unleſs they Repent, &amp; ceaſe to do wickedly.</note> But true peace is the portion of the Righteous, who in faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs follow the Lord; and peace to thoſe that love Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs, who take delight to walk in the way of the Lord, which is a way of holineſs; and without holineſs none can ſee the Lord; therefore turn unto him I beſeech you all, and embrace the light of his Spirit, and make no longer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay; let not his Locks be wet with the drops of the night, whilſt he ſtands knocking at the door of your hearts, but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen unto him that he may come in and ſup with you, and you with him, that ſo you may come by living experience to witneſs the fulfilling of thoſe weighty ſayings that ſtand upon Record in the holy Scriptures, and thoſe Propheſies ſpoken of by the Prophets in the dayes of old, who ſaid, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, I will pour out my Spirit upon all fleſh, upon Sons and upon Daughters, upon Servants and upon Hand-maids, and they ſhall Propheſie; I will write my Law in their hearts, and put my Spirit in their inward parts; I will be their God, and they ſhall be my people; I will be their Father, and they ſhall be my Sons and Daughters:</hi> This is our God, and in whom we have believed, that is good and gracious unto the Children of men, who gives gifts unto the Rebellious; for thus ſaith the Lord, <hi>I gave them my good Spirit to inſtruct them, but they rebelled againſt it:</hi> and ſome there were of old that did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight to the Spirit of Grace, and ſuch there are in this Age, but if they do not obey the Spirit of Grace, their end will be miſerable.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:53533:13"/>
               <head>A few words to thoſe that have Apoſtatized from the Truth, and ſo Conclude.</head>
               <p>ANd now you Backſliders, let your eye be turned unto the Lord in the light of his Son, from whom you are fallen, and look for his fiery indignation to take hold of the tranſgreſſion to deſtroy the Adverſary of your ſouls, that hath drawn you aſide from the Lord, and be willing to bear his indignation becauſe you have ſinned againſt him that through Judgment you may be redeemed to your firſt Love, and to do your firſt Works, leſt the Lord come unto you quickly, and take vengeance upon you to the full, and grind you to pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ye fallen Stars that have loſt your light, that are drawn down from Heaven to the earth by the ſtrength of the Dragons power: O conſider in time vvhere you are vvandering like Fugitives and Vagabonds in the earth, and be not high-mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but fear and conſider from vvhence you are fallen, and hovv you have forgotten the dayes of your tenderneſs, and have let hardneſs of heart come over you again: O behold the deſolation, the ruine, &amp; the breaches that are come upon you, by reaſon of your Wanderings from your firſt tenderneſs, vvhen the Lord broke in upon you and tendered your hearts in his everlaſting loving kindneſs, but you have not prized his love, but have wandered from his pure light: O conſider the goodneſs of the Lord, and turn again unto him, that he may ſhew you mercy; remember how the Lord ſhewed <hi>John</hi> things that were to come, how that there ſhould be War in Heaven, <hi>Michael and his Angels againſt the Dragon and his Angels;</hi> and <hi>John</hi> ſaw to the end of the war, that the Dragon and his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, could not prevail againſt <hi>Michael</hi> and his Angels, but
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53533:14"/>was overcome, and was caſt out of Heaven to the earth, and their place was no more found in Heaven; and this made them rage becauſe they had no place in heaven; ſo the Dragon was wrath with the Woman that brought forth the Man-Child, and he caſt out his floods af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her, even the floods of Perſecution, and made War with the remnant of her Seed, that kept the Teſtimony of Jeſus, and the Word of God, and in their Wrath they blaſphemed the Name of God, his Tabernacle, and them that dwell in Heaven; and this <hi>John</hi> ſaw in the Spirit, which reacheth unto this preſent time; for have we not ſeen the day in this our age, that many of you entred into the Heavenly Profeſſion, and had for a time a ſmall part in the heavenly fellowſhip of the knowledge of God; but after you had known him, not glorifying him as God, nor liking to retain him in your knowledge, but growing heady, and high-minded, and giving your power to the Dragon to make War with the Saints, thoſe that have kept their habitation in the Truth here begins the War, for they have laboured with you, and ſought you with much tenderneſs, that you might not be utterly driven away, that you might not be caſt out of the heavenly fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and fall into utter deſolation; but you ſtill joyning with the Dragon to make War with them, ſo there was no help for you, but that you muſt be overcome, and ſo be caſt out of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven into the earth, and this hath been the cauſe of your rage and anger, becauſe you were caſt out by them that have kept the word of their Teſtimony in faithfulneſs; for this was that which <hi>John</hi> ſaw, that they overcame by the word of their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, and the blood of the Lamb: and O with what dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, care and patience have the faithful Brethren ſtrove with you, ſeeking your Return, but O how hath their care been flighted by you, and had in deriſion among you, who have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven reproachful terms to thoſe Meetings that have been ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53533:14"/>on this account, for the repairing of Breaches, and build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the waſte places, and gathering into Peace and Unity where the Faithful Brethren have been very diligent to build up the Ruines and Deſolations; but O how have they been by ſome ſet at nought, and ill requited for their labour of Love, even by ſuch who have been ready to lay waſte, and make Breaches, and ſow Diſſention, and cauſe Diviſions among Brethren; but ſaid the Apoſtle, <hi>Mark them that cauſe Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions amongſt you, and avoid them, for they that gather not with us, ſcatter abroad;</hi> and I right well know that none that abides not in the unity of the Spirit ever gathers to God, let them pretend never ſo fair; but it is poſſible that they may gather to themſelves by their feigned words and fair ſpeeches, but they ſhall not long continue, but their folly ſhall be made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt; thoſe that are heady and high minded, and will not take counſel of the Lord, nor hearken to the voice of his Servants, but are ready to ſay in a way of contempt, as <hi>Miriam</hi> did in the dayes of old, <hi>Hath the Lord ſpake only by Moſes, hath he not alſo ſpake by us?</hi> but the Lord brought her to Judgment that ſpake contemptuouſly of his Servant <hi>Moſes,</hi> as ſome are ready to ſay at this day of the Ancients of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> by reaſon of their care over the flock and family of God; the ſame ſpirit alſo is ready to riſe up againſt them, as it did in the dayes of old in them that ſaid, <hi>You Sons of Levi, you take too much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you,</hi> and ſo now, ſuch as are careleſs themſelves, and idle themſelves, are ready to ſay of others, they take too much upon them, and ſo ſlight the labours and travels of the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who have the care of the Churches upon them, and have born the burthen and heat of the day, and have been in perils by Sea, and perils by Land, taking care that things might be well among Friends every where, and that true love and unity might be encreaſed, and that which is evil kept down; and this is well pleaſing unto the Lord, and this work the Lord hath bleſſed and proſpered, and made it effectual for
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:53533:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>good, and thoſe who abide in the truth, have ſeen a ſervice in it for the Lord, notwithſtanding all the oppoſition; for this we know that ſuch as oppoſe the work of the Lord will not proſper, let them cover themſelves with never ſo fair pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, with greater enjoyments of the Lord, this co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering will prove too narrow to hide them from the wrath of the Lord, when they are appoſtatized from the truth, and from the comely order in the Unity of the Spirit, and from the followſhip of the Goſpel of peace, ſuch as came forth with us, but were not of us; So they went forth from us that it might be manifeſt to all people, that they are not of us.</p>
               <p>But oh ye backſliders that have appoſtatized from the truth, and have crucified the Lord afreſh, and put him to open ſhame, you that have not wholly ſinned out your day, Return, return unto the Lord that he may heal your backſlidings, and ſhew mercy unto you, and love you freely for his own names ſake, who hath moved in my heart, in the bowels of his own com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions to call upon you to return unto him, that he may ſhew you favor, before his anger break forth againſt you, &amp; his decree be ſealed, that you periſh not in your gain-ſaying &amp; Apoſtacy, and the earth ſwallow you up, and you become miſerable for ever; therefore Conſider, if it be not too late, for there is mercy with him, and bowels of compaſſion for all that truly ſeek him in uprightneſs of heart. Thus I have cleared my Conſcience whether you will hear or forbear, from one that travels for the proſperity of <hi>Sion,</hi> and loves Unity and peace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong brethren; truly deſiring the welfare of all people that they may come to the knowledge of the truth and be ſaved; and that theſe that do already know it may abide in it for ever and ever. which is the true and hearty ſincere deſire of your true Friend, that ſeeks for peace and Unity.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Cyrenceſter <date>the <hi>2d</hi> day of the <hi>9th</hi> month, 1675.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Theophila Townſend.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
